Inventory of the James Barron Hope Papers (II) 1820-1923
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Personal Correspondence, 1842-1920. (Box-folder 1:1-7)
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., 10 June 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Their wedding anniversary; profuse praise for her role as his wife; saw several of their friends; since she, his mother, and their children are well, he is content; promises to take care of himself, since in doing so he is also taking care of her.
    Bears ALS from James [Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p. Will write tonight; she and Annie must comfort one another.
    Includes ALS from James B[arron] Hope, [Richmond, Virginia], to Jane [A. Barron Hope], n.p. He loves and prays for her to be good; will send her carriage this week. 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 11 June 1861., 11 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Her letter's tone of Christian fortitude lifted him; he will see her again here on earth; plans to rebuild their home and replace household goods; keep a strong faith; anxious to hear of Jane's health; don't listen to rumors; will be going to W[illia]msburg next; refutes friend's suggestion that [Williamsburg] should be evacuated; in reply to her request for a lock of hair, he thinks he has already given her one; compliments on being a wonderful wife; trust God.
    Bears ALS from James [Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to Jane [A. (Barron) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina]. Words of encouragement; hopes to tell grandchildren stories of the war of southern independence.
    Includes ALS from [James Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to Jane [Barron Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina]. Will send her carriage; be a good girl. 1 page.
    Includes ALS from [James Barron Hope], [Richmond, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina]. Lock of hair and brief note. 1 page.
  - Mary [Blake, sister of Jane A. (Barron) Hope], Naval Academy, [Annapolis, Maryland] to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., 12 June [1861?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Received a long letter from Virginia [sister of both], which she knows will please Jane; yesterday the graduating class of the academy presented her [Mary Blake] with a "handsome sword;" her spirits have lifted somewhat; warns not to expect her to visit until she investigates the matter further; wants James to write and have Annie write a postscript; gives her love to the servants and family.
  - Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], Warrenton, [North Carolina], to James [Barron Hope], n.p., 17 June 1861., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:3)
    How much she and the children miss him; her new friends in Warrenton are quite pleasant; she worries about the military defense of the South, since it has "so many accessable points"
    Including ALS, 18 June 1861 from Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], Warrenton, North Carolina, to James [Barron Hope], n.p. Worry over no word from James; please get a prescription for the baby if possible; asks when he can visit; wants to know his living arrangements; how busy the children keep her; counts their many blessings when compared to others. 2 pages.
  - James [Barron Hope], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 22 June 1861., 4 pages. (Box-folder 1:3)
    His great affection for her; his quarters and clothes are agreeable; why the North will go bankrupt, and why the South will endure; almost 10,000 men [Confederates] in Williamsburg; the 1st North Carolina Reg[imen]t under Gen[era]l [Daniel Harvey] Hill is remarkable for its "orderly behavior in camp and its gallantry under fire;" Hill is "a good soldier, an earnest Christian, and respected by all who know him for his piety;" he has not mentioned their "Foreign Relatives." 4 pages. ALS.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], [Williamsburg, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Contains a copy of a hymn he found; terms of affection; superiority of Southern troops in recent combat; report [mentions Lincoln] of only 29 men enlisting as of late in New York City.
    Includes NwsCl from [James Barron Hope], [Williamsburg, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Poem, "Beyond." 1 page.
  - [James Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 25 June 1861., 2 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Asks three questions he had forgotten in his last letter: if an acquaintance of his as he [James Barron Hope] had asked; how they have "arranged about the drought;" and if she would like for him to have her big wardrobe chest sent to her; the feeling at headquarters is that the war will be short, and he prays for it to be so.
    Including ALS from James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. His joy at her good spirits, and his own good health. 1 page.
  - J[ames Barron] Hope, n.p., to Rosa [Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 25 June [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    How she may form her character while in her current position, staying with his mother and wife; be economical, avoid indolence, learn an occupation, and above all else, avoid frivolous, fashionable people; his mother is an example of the aforementioned qualities; her [Rosa's] father is in good health.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 26 June 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
    Received letter from Uncle Sam[uel Barron], which requires his presence in Richmond; appears to have gained an appointment to a "safe" job as Commodore [French] For[r]est's secretary; delay sending letters until further notice; love for her and faith in God.
    Bears ALS from James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. This letter is also to her.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane Barron Hope and Anne Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Will send the carriage; loves them; P.S. instructs children to remind their mother [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope] to date and number her letters. 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope], Portsmouth, [Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?], ? July [1861]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Met Mr. White, who married a relative of his, Sarah [Eskridge?]; sat in the chair of his grand-father [George] Hope; faith in God; don't get depressed; wants to know about the children.
  - John Tyler, "Sherwood Forest", [Charles City County, Virginia], to [John B. Magruder], [Yorktown, Virginia], 11 July 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Introduction to his friend and esteemed neighbor, [James Barron Hope], who requested the introduction; describes him [James Barron Hope] as intellectual, honorable, brave, trustworthy, etc.; [James Barron Hope]'s leading object is to be the historian of the war; to write a true narrative, he would like to see passing events with his own eye; wishes him [John B. Magruder] additional glories.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Portsmouth, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], [post 14 July 1861 - ante 18 July 1861]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Charmed by her last letter, which described their daughter [Janie] chasing fireflies; his job is going well; keep saving money just in case anything happens; he has been visiting some friends, who have treated him with every kindness.
  - Mary [Blake, sister of Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Baron) Hope], Hampton, Virginia, 18[?] July [1861?]., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Has news from Virginia [sister of both], who has married in Hamburg [Germany on 21 June 1861?], and began her honeymoon tour of Europe; feels that "poor Papa [Commodore James Barron] would look back with pleasure at their interest in visiting a place fraught with kindly remembrances of the attentions paid him in those dark days of his unjust suspension;" Virginia has complained of wanting frequent letters from Jane and James [Barron Hope]; is unsure whether she will be able to vacation; she [Mary Blake] is impatient for a letter from James, who is now the master of a ship, and delighted with the position's advantages.
  - J[ames] B[arron] Hope, n.p., to Jane [Barron Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], [post 21 June 1861 - ante 30 July 1861?]., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Encloses the wonderful doll he had promised her; wants her to teach her little sister to say her prayers, spell, and count; tell Mrs. Lacy that he believes "under Lincoln's Proclamation, the package for Mr. Drew is contraband..." and he shall confiscate it; he will eat [th]em [?] with a "lively remembrance of her;" be very good.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Please read Jane's letter to her; news from headquarters that the enemy was "driven back three times with great slaughter" [at 1st Bull Run, 21 July 1861]; this compensates and more for the N[orth] W[est] disaster[Battle of Rich Mountain, 11 July 1861]. 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Portsmouth, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 23 July 1861., 5 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Her last letter told him that [Nan]nie has been sick again; ask the doctor if she should have a change of air; if so, take her and Missee Sarah [servant?] to Jones' Springs for a month; his uncle and his family are in W[illia]msburg, and her father has decided to leave; her friends are not in danger; if her parents want to leave and need assistance, he will help them in every way that he can; very excited, as he just received news of a glorious Confederate victory [1st Bull Run, 21 July 1861]; his Uncle Sam[uel Barron] is being sent to North Carolina to take charge of coast defenses; keep praying.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], [Portsmouth, Virginia], to [Jane B. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Assures her that " Gen[era]l Lee thinks Norfolk perfectly safe." [Note on envelope: "The Yorktown is off Craney Is[lan]d! ! ! So I hear." 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 30 July 1861., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Wrote mother yesterday, but was dissatisfied by its brevity; attended church twice; the second service was a Catholic Mass in honor of the victory at Manassas; description of the sanctuary; "Republican simplicity", or diversity of class in the congregation; enjoyment of the music; just received her letter; wants to know if Janey is getting better; visited Capt[ain] Clark[e?] along with Mr. Anderson; on 29 July visited several friends with Aunt M[ary, his mother's sister], but no one is as pretty or wonderful as she; her image is impressed upon his soul; he has thought of studying Divinity, and it is not out of the question; his love for the family.
  - [James Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?], 31 July [18]61., 4 pages. AL. (Box-folder 1:4)
    How he treasures her letters; is he correct in thinking that Baby Jane's health is slowly improving?; his uncle's [Samuel Barron] position is delicate, since he has not yet been ordered to hoist his flag, and until then he cannot take a secretary; made an offer to her brother to take Mrs. Whiting [Annie's mother?] and place her in Warrenton with Annie and James' mother; included Annie's father in the invitation, but expects that they will go to Gloucester; do not worry about her family members close to the Yankees, since the recent disaster [1st Bull Run, 21 July 1861] has really shaken them.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Norfolk, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 16 August [18]61., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Thankful that Annie has gotten better; he has sent a box to her, and another one is at Warrenton Depot; will start writing to her on Mondays and Fridays; love to the family.
    Includes ALS from James [Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Regrets she is ill; recommends placing a box of hot sand on her face; expresses love and gratitude. 1 page.
    Bears postscript from James [Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Enclosed certificate of deposit for $25; stress to economize.
  - [James Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 17 August [18]61., 1 page. AL. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Received her note; surprised by her offer to send him money, since he sent her $25 in his last letter.
    Includes ALS, 19 August 1861, from James [Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina?]. Requests that she make a cape with a red flannel cross on the outside, to send to the Confederate troops for the coming winter; great enthusiasm and encouragement for the idea; attended church in Norfolk on Sunday, and dined with the Camps; has been told that her aunt and uncle are well.
  - James [Barron Hope], Norfolk, Virginia, to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina?], 18 August [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Is not in need of her generous offer of money; "much provoked" that she has not yet received his package; joy after learning that Baby Jane's health has improved; Uncle Sam[uel Barron] is in Norfolk and sends his love; asks her to make a large coat to send to a Confederate soldier.
  - [James Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 28 August [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Appreciated both Janey's note and the bank draft very much; thinks that she should stay in Warrenton for the winter; both the cost and the possibility of further conflict dictate it; misses them very much, but is holding up well; the low cost of living in Warrenton will help in rebuilding their house later; twice mentions possibility of [Union] Gen[era]l [John Ellis] Wool attacking, with his close to 30,000 men; the winter will soon drift by; he will bring home wonderful items to put in the children's stockings; tell him if "our mother" needs anything; he has a good wardrobe for the winter; enjoys and is doing well in his job working for the Commo[dore, French Forrest].
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 29 [August 18]61., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Invested their money in two $500 and one $100 Confederate bonds; he will explain why when he writes his mother; is urging Clay's[?] claims at the [Navy?] Department vigorously; inquires how Rosa [a Hope relative staying with Annie and his mother] is getting along; a force is leaving for the coast of North Carolina, and in his despair of not being able to go, he cries, then writes "how strange an animal is man!"; love to the family.
    Bears postscript from James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Saw the pretty wives of some departing officers, and these women didn't cry; he can't understand it.
    Bears postscript from [James Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Rec[eive]d letter from Hon[orable] Robert Tyler assuring him of his services in Clay's behalf; "he writes very warmly."
  - Tazewell Taylor, n.p., to James Barron Hope, n.p., 29 August 1861., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    The Confederate Loan has been made in Hope's name, for the sum of $1,100; the bonds have not yet been printed; and until they are he [James Barron Hope] has the option of taking coupon bonds instead of registered bonds; the bonds carry interest from this day.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], n.p., 31 August 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
    Grieves that the newspaper report he sent her was erroneous; Uncle Sam has been captured in North Carolina, but not of his own fault; he [Uncle Sam] will be treated with respect due his rank; thank God that James did not take the position as his secretary, which he considered.
    Bears ALS from James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope], n.p., asking if Rosa [a Hope relative of James Barron Hope] is annoying her; glad that she liked the dress; thank you for the letter, which was well-timed.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 2 September [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Apologizes for not answering her letters; glad that she likes her dress; take good care of it, because if the war is protracted she may be without another gown so fine for quite some time; love for his children; glad that his letters please her; counts their many blessings "since the beginning of these troubles;" agrees that Hampton's destruction by fire was sad, but he would have done it himself rather than allowing its use as winter quarters for the enemy; "Drunk or sober...Magruder did well and wisely;" claims that the Yankees planned to burn it; Magruder had told him previously of this possibility; still believes [CSA General John B.] Magruder to be a great and moral commander; "the Yankees seem to think that the "road to 'Richmond' is up the Peninsula...;" predicts that if a fight occurs Magruder will follow the Yankees into Newport News; Clay's [?] appointment seems secure, through both himself and Mr. Rob[ert] Tyler; he worshipped at the Catholic church again; will write again tomorrow; kiss everyone for him.
  - James [Barron Hope],[Norfolk, Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 7 September [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Just received her letter; plans to make Jennie a carriage; asks what kind of shoes she wants; gratitude to Dr. Howard for his care of Jennie; Clay has been appointed Q[uarte]r Master and Captain in the Confederate army; opinion that [CSA general Earl] Van Dorn and his Texan troops can defend Texas well against invasion; has no more doubt of the Confederacy's success than he does in the Christian religion.
    Includes ALS, 7 [September 1861] from James [Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]; Explanation of difference between registered and coupon bonds; why he views coupon bonds as superior; the great kindness of his aunt, Mrs. [Samuel] Barron; concern for his mother's health; do not despond, but instead trust in God; delight in learning that Baby Jane climbed the steps; has written a poem on the Battle of Bethel, and plans to write Gen[era]l Magruder about it; kiss his mother and the girls for him. 4 pages.
    Includes Ms from [James Barron Hope], [Norfolk, Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina]. Diagram of belt for hiding valuables; instructions for burning the note after mastering its concept.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], [post 7 September 1861 - ante 3 February 1862]. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Relieved that she is now well; will send her box on the 13th; is saving a good amount of money; Mr. Chisman is a quarter master and will be stationed at Jamestown, [Virginia]; Mr. Chisman [?] has the same position; love to the family.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 14 September [18]61., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Attended church in Norfolk; attended the Catholic evening service with [George] Camp; visited some friends; her mother's brave resolution in looking her position in the face [her mother is terminally ill?]; puzzlement over Clay's not writing; assurance that he will help her mother in every possible way; mentions that previous and forthcoming confederate troop additions, and predicts that [Union General John Ellis] Wool will "have his obituary written before he sees Norfolk, unless per chance he may go up in a balloon for that purpose;" waiting makes his Confederate force stronger; stresses that if Norfolk is attacked; she must resign her will and let him do his duty like a Christian gentleman; reminds her that death is only a temporary absence from those who believe Christ and his resurrection; kiss Mother and the "little chicks" for him.
  - Jane A. [(Barron)] Hope, Warrenton, North Carolina, to Imogene Barron, n.p., 7 November 1861., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Surprise at how quickly time passes, especially in regards to the growth of young people; invitation to visit Warrenton, which she and Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope] appreciate for its inhabitants; is pleased to hear that her [Imogene Barron] brother Samuel has returned from California; mentions her two grandchildren; James [B. Hope] will send Jane anything that Imogene gives him, and that he will help her in any way possible.
  - Jane [A.] Barron [Hope], Warrenton, North Carolina, to James [Barron Hope],[Portsmouth, Virginia], 20 December 1861., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Her strongest wishes for blessings and happiness for him; relays Jane Barron's message that she wants to see him soon; story about young Janie and her friend Annie Mallory; her opinion of the 'political horizon' as being one of "gloomy portent...But God can save us, I know..."
  - Jane A. [Barron] Hope, Warrenton, North Carolina, to James [Barron Hope], n.p., 26 December 1861., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Her best wishes for him; thankfulness for both his recent letter, with a picture of her, and for being such a wonderful son.
    Includes AL [torn] from [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], to [James Barron Hope], n.p. Her sympathy for their family and friends near their old home, since their old church now lies in ruins, and their friends are scattered. 1 page.
  - James [Barron Hope], n.p., to [Jane A. (Barron) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 2 January [18]62., 6 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Worries about her health; thanks her for both her recent letter and her care since his youth; the Commodore returned today, and they talked for several hours; he will write a letter to Aunt V[irginia] tomorrow, or try; his writing for the newspaper is "really an amusement;" don't worry about this extra work, as it is very easy.
  - J. Wilcox, Raleigh, [North Carolina], to Ja[me]s B. Hope, Ports[mouth, Virginia], 3 January [1862]., 1 page. Telegram. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Dr. Howard thinks that his mother [Jane A. (Barron) Hope] is very sick; tells him to come immediately.
  - [James Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to Annie [B. (Whiting) Hope],[Warrenton, North Carolina], 29 May 1862., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Has only received one of her letters recently; he has written her profusely in the vain attempt of assuring her of his "unutterable devotion;" is currently Judge Advocate in court [officer of proceedings in a court-martial]; thankful to God for his mercies.
  - [James Barron Hope], n.p., to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], [post 1 June 1862 - ante 11 April 1865]., 2 pages. Incomplete. AL. (Box-folder 1:5)
    Instructions on sending Confederate coupon bonds to him; wants her to always have at least $6,000; assuages her loneliness by giving the example of Gen[era]l Lee, or the poor privates, who never get to visit their families; sent her [Edward] Bulwer [Lytton]'s latest novel; thank Mrs. A [?] for keeping Annie and the children under her roof; wants long letters; love for her and the children.
  - James [Barron Hope], Richmond, [Virginia], to [Annie B. (Whiting) Hope], [Warrenton, North Carolina], 4 June [18]62., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:5)